A Guide to the Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Carter Glass 1858-1946, and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2913
This collection consists of ca. 215,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of Carter Glass and Mrs. John Boatwright on March 29, 1948.
Biographical/Historical Information
Perhaps the most telling comment about Carter Glass came from President Franklin Roosevelt, who called Glass an "Unreconstructed Rebel." Roosevelt meant exactly what the capital "R" on Rebel implies. As the Senate's last surviving member born in the antebellum South, Glass unapologetically fought to retain a society in which property-owning, white males sat at the top of the pyramid. In that regard, he was a man of his times.
Carter Glass was born just as the year 1858 began, into a newspaper family that did not back away from a fight. Robert Henry Glass, Carter's father, owned the Lynchburg Daily Republican, the dominant Democratic newspaper in southwestern Virginia. In the summer of 1860, while Robert was away on business, his associate editor, George Hardwicke, killed a rival newspaperman who accused Glass of using his position as postmaster of Lynchburg to prevent the delivery of his competitor's papers. The elder Glass himself almost got into a duel, but his wife swore out warrants on both parties, and the matter was settled with canes rather than pistols. These lessons were not lost on Carter Glass, a scrapper in his youth who, as the eventual publisher of his own newspaper, almost came to a duel with a cross-town rival.
During Reconstruction, there were few opportunities for the younger Glass to receive much formal education. At the age of 13, he was taken out of school and apprenticed as a printer with his father. From that point on, he learned on his own, reading Plato, Edmund Burke and Shakespeare, and his love of such intellectual pursuits never waned. Later, when he owned his own papers, he published articles about the true identity of Shakespeare, the meaning of the biblical stories as history and other such topics.
Carter worked six years for his father, then moved with him to Petersburg, Va., to work on The Petersburg News. When the reporting job young Glass wanted did not materialize, he took a job as a clerk in the auditor's office of the Atlantic, Mississippi and Ohio Railroad back in Lynchburg. Robert accepted one of his son's political editorials, and soon after, 22-year-old Carter was offered a job as reporter on the Lynchburg News. Within a few years, he became the paper's editor and also served as clerk for the city of Lynchburg. With what looked to be a bright future, at the age of 28, Glass married his landlord's daughter, a school teacher from Lynchburg, and they eventually had four children.
In 1888, with the help of some friends, he bought the Lynchburg News, and two years later, he purchased the Daily Republican, once owned by his father. In the meantime, the elder Glass returned to Lynchburg and took over the editorship of The Advance, becoming Carter's rival. During a family feud, Robert stormed over to his son's offices and asked him where he had come up with the nonsense printed in the News. Carter pointed to a clipping his father had written earlier and said, "In my boyish pride of my father, I used to keep a scrapbook."
Eventually, he bought the paper his father was editing and became the only publisher in town. Well respected both inside and outside his community, he used his influence to champion politicians who ran against what he felt were Democratic politicians promoting bad fiscal policy. Two important events occurred in 1896: his father died, and Carter went as a delegate to the Democratic National Convention. There he heard William Jennings Bryan speak for free silver in his famous speech: "Thou shalt not press down upon the brow of labor this crown of thorns. Thou shalt not crucify mankind upon a cross of gold!" Glass would later repudiate Bryan's philosophy, but the adventure hooked him on politics. As a politician, he was never in doubt
In 1899, Glass was elected to the Virginia Senate. Two years later, as a delegate to the State Constitutional Convention, Glass became instrumental in pushing through the convention a proposal to proclaim a new state constitution outright without submitting it to anyone, thus disenfranchising those who had gained the right to vote under the 14th and 15th amendments. Almost four decades later, when President Franklin Roosevelt wanted to abolish poll taxes throughout the South, Glass defended the plank he himself had put into the Virginia Constitution and stated that "the President displays a very superficial knowledge of the subject."
Even as he worked to disenfranchise certain segments of society, he had a soft spot in his heart for individual blacks. In the midst of the fight over the Federal Reserve Bill, Glass made a special trip home to Lynchburg to appear at the manslaughter trial of his black servant. He took the witness stand, "swore that William was the best Negro that ever lived in the United States" and pleaded to keep him from imprisonment. When William was fined $200, Congressman Glass reached into his pocket, pulled out a roll of bills, paid the fine, then rushed back to Washington, D.C.
In 1902, at the age of 44, Glass was elected to the United States House of Representatives. To those who did not know him, he appeared sickly and frail. The 5-foot-4-inch Glass had dropped to 100 pounds and walked around on tiptoes to avoid jarring his sensitive stomach. This malady was not uncommon for Glass. Four years earlier, doctors warned him that his irregular eating habits and intense working habits had almost ruined his digestion, as well as caused a number of other bothersome ills. "Rest," his doctor ordered; but it was a futile request.
His colleagues in the House soon learned that this little man was not to be taken lightly. Within two years, he was appointed to the Committee on Banking and Currency and threw himself into the study of finance just as heartily as he had earlier delved into questions about Shakespeare when he was a newspaper editor.
The Banking Panic of 1907 put the Banking and Currency committee in the spotlight, and Glass found himself chairman when his friend Woodrow Wilson was elected president. Initial efforts at resolving the problems raised by the 1907 panic, though, were met with frustration. Essentially, legislators were concerned about two issues: a banking system that was prone to panics (1907's event was not rare), and a currency that was not responsive to changes in demand. On the makeup of a reserve system to address those problems, there was disagreement over the control of such an institution: Should private banks have control over the eventual Federal Reserve System, or should their input be confined to decentralized banks within the system?
Carter Glass--who favored decentralized power--was particularly adamant on this question, and his role in developing the legislation is an example of how his Jeffersonian ideas of democracy, along with his tenacious spirit, helped shape one of the country's most important pieces of financial legislation. After working tirelessly on the subject for five years, the election of 1912 brought an opening: not only did it usher Wilson into the White House, but it also gave Glass' party control of both the House and Senate.
Glass wasted no time. He began drafting legislation with Wilson before the newly elected president even took office, and by December of the following year, the Federal Reserve Act was passed and signed into law. Glass was thrilled: "The thing which had been vainly discussed and intermittently attempted for 20 years had finally been accomplished!"
Essentially, in constructing the Federal Reserve Act with Wilson, Glass had repackaged the previous Republican administration's proposal, the economist Milton Friedman would later write, making it even more conservative. Instead of a centralized bank under private banker control, Glass, of course, wanted decentralized banks under private control. (The claim that the Federal Reserve Act was a modified form of the Aldrich plan was also made in Glass' day, and it was a notion he detested. In a 1922 speech before the Senate, Glass called the idea "a total misunderstanding," and said "no greater misconception was ever projected in this Senate Chamber ...") It was Wilson who suggested an altruistic board of governors appointed by the executive branch. Even though he may not have entirely liked that idea, Glass and his sharp tongue helped guarantee the bill's passage.
During the coming European war, Glass supported Wilson and the struggle for a lasting peace. At the end of 1919, he was named Wilson's Secretary of the Treasury, the first cabinet officer from Virginia since the elder Glass' commander, John Floyd, was Secretary of War in Buchanan's administration. As such, Glass favored rebuilding Europe, including the defeated Germany, and pushed for American financial assistance. Although as head of the Treasury, Glass was in charge of enforcing prohibition laws, his greatest domestic concern had to do with the vast amount of borrowing for stock market speculation. Glass wanted the banks voluntarily to restrict their lending for stock purchases and warned about the consequences if nothing was done.
Exactly one year after he took over at the Treasury, the popular Glass was appointed to the Senate in 1920 to succeed Thomas S. Martin of Virginia, who died in late 1919. Glass would remain a Virginia senator until his death.
When Glass' predictions about the economy came true in 1929, he first went to work defending his original Federal Reserve legislation, then proceeded in 1931 to write a banking reform bill to provide the Federal Reserve Board with greater control over speculative credit. Thus began an important period wherein Glass and the rest of the nation, reeling from a series of financial panics and rampant bank closures, reconsidered what type of financial system was best for the country.
Briefly, some of the laws enacted:
* Glass-Steagall Act of 1932: The piece of legislation that keeps Glass' name in the news today, largely because of its provisions that separated commercial and investment banking; current reformers hope to mend that split. The Act also permitted the use of U.S. government securities as collateral for Federal Reserve notes.
* Banking Act of 1933: Established the Federal Deposit Insurance Corp.-set the insurance level at $2,500 per depositor; placed control of open market operations under the Federal Reserve.
* Reconstruction Finance Corp. (1933): Permitted Federal Reserve to issue loans directly to businesses.
* Securities and Exchange Act: Provided for minimum margins on purchases of securities on credit.
* Banking Act of 1935: Created the Federal Open Market Committee; Federal Reserve Board becomes the Board of Governors, with terms set at 14 years; Secretary of the Treasury and Comptroller of the Currency were removed from the Board.
Glass was not always on the winning side of these new laws, including in his opposition to federal deposit insurance. As Friedman and Anna Schwartz tell it in their Monetary History of the United States: "[Glass] had opposed a similar provision at the time of the passage of the original Federal Reserve Act. Glass believed that the solution was reform of the practices of commercial banks and introduced several bills to that end. None received the support of the administration or of the Reserve System, and none was passed."
In 1932, the political party he had been a member of for many years began to head down a path Glass did not care to take. Although he was said to like Franklin Roosevelt personally, he could not bring himself to trust anyone who sought public office with Roosevelt's vigor. Glass had also locked horns with Roosevelt when the latter was assistant secretary of the Navy and wanted to keep the Coast Guard under the Navy's jurisdiction after the end of World War I. Glass, as the head of Treasury, insisted it return to Treasury's control and won the point. Despite his misgivings, Glass got out of his sickbed to defend Roosevelt against Hoover's attacks. Roosevelt, in turn, offered Glass the Treasury. In poor health, Glass turned down the office, but he also knew that he and Roosevelt did not agree on fundamental economic issues. Glass tried to keep their disagreements private, but in a very short time, the Roosevelt administration would give him fits. The New Deal came along and took his mind off everything else, according to a flattering biography, even his prized Jersey cows at his home at Montview Farm, Va.
Although in public Glass continued to support the Roosevelt administration, he openly fought some Roosevelt initiatives and worked tirelessly to fight against what he considered unconstitutional interference by the federal government in private affairs. But the fact that the New Deal carried all but two states in 1936 did not surprise Glass: "It is well nigh impossible to beat a five billion dollar campaign fund," he quipped.
For the first time in years he did not participate in the construction of the party platform in 1936, and he spent the next four years working for a balanced budget and states' rights, usually behind the scenes. In 1937, however, he went on the radio to attack the White House's attempt to pack the Supreme Court. Glass won the battle. In 1940, as he had done four years earlier, he fought against the nomination of Roosevelt, but gave his support when the Democrat was nominated for a third term.
Having been a widower for the previous three years, Glass remarried in 1940 at the age of 82. Although Glass' character had been "carved out of unblemished granite," according to Harry Byrd, the junior senator from his home state, the man himself had begun to allow the illnesses which had plagued him for most of his life to slow him down. For all intents and purposes, the father of the Federal Reserve System retired from public life within two years.
Finally, at the age of 88, Glass died of congestive heart failure in his apartment at the Mayflower Hotel in Washington, D.C. Out of respect for the senator from Virginia, the Senate suspended business and adjourned for the day. "A link with the Old South is broken in the passing of your distinguished husband," President Truman wrote to the second Mrs. Glass. "To the end he glorified in the title of 'Unreconstructed Rebel.'"
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Glass consist of personal and professional papers including correspondence, speeches, notes and memoranda, documents, printed matter, photographs, clippings and miscellaneous material. Much of the collection centers on banking and currency legislation, in the enactment of which Glass was active while in both Houses of Congress and while serving as Secretary of the Treasury.
Subjects include: the Federal Reserve Bank Act and Federal Reserve system; the Federal Farm Loan Act; branch banks; currency [reform] bill of 1913; Emergency Banking Act, 1933; the Banking Act of 1933 (Glass- Steagall Act) to establish the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; the Bank Bill of 1935; opposition to the National Industrial Recovery Act; the National Labor Relations Act; the Bank Holding Company Bill; and the Office of Price Administration.
Additional topics include World Wars I and II, particularly their domestic economic aspects; the League of Nations; the World Court; Democratic Party platforms and policies; the presidential elections of 1912, 1920, 1924, 1928, and 1940; Senator Huey P. Long; Franklin D. Roosevelt and the New Deal; the attempted packing of the Supreme Court, 1937; neutrality legislation; disarmament; regulation of the coal industry; child labor; anti-lynching law; immigration restriction (especially Chinese in Hawaii); Muscle Shoals; trade with Russia; diplomatic relations with the Vatican; Four-Power Treaty; soldiers' bonus bill; tariffs and protectionism; and national defense.
Virginia topics of concern to Glass or his constituents include poll tax elimination; Negro suffrage; highways; the University of Virginia Board of Visitors; patronage requests from Lynchburg, Roanoke, and Bedford, Campbell, Floyd, Montgomery, and Roanoke Counties, Va.; the Woodrow Wilson Foundation; a national Patrick Henry shrine at "Red Hill"; the gubernatorial election of 1924; Bishop James Cannon, prohibition and the Anti-saloon League; the Skyline Drive; Spotsylvania Battlefield Park; the Woodrow Wilson Foundation; the Virginia Fight For Freedom Committee; and operation of the Lynchburg News and Advance.
Miscellaneous items of interest include a letter describing the early life of Booker T. Washingrton, election tickets for 1848, a 1906 recipe book, and letters concerning Glass' belief in the Baconian theory of Shakespeare authorship.
In addition to speeches by Glass there are speeches by Edwin A. Alderman, Harry Byrd, Sr., George M. Coffin, Gilbert M. Hitchcock, Henry Cabot Lodge, Francis Pickens Miller, Al Smith, and Henry St. George Tucker.
Among the many correspondents are: Edwin A. Alderman, Newton Baker, Ray Stannard Baker, Alben Barkley, Bernard Baruch, William E. Borah, Chester Bowles, John Stewart Bryan, William Jennings Bryan, Harry F. Byrd, Richard E. Byrd, Calvin Coolidge, John W. Daniel, Josephus Daniels, Colgate W. Darden, Westmoreland Davis, F. A. Delano, the Democratic National Committee, Marriner S. Eccles, James A. Farley, Douglas Southall Freeman, James A. Garfield, Samuel Gompers, Cary Grayson, Charles S. Hamlin, W. P. G. Harding, Warren G. Harding, J. Edgar Hoover, Herbert Hoover, Edwin M. House, Cordell Hull, Harold Ickes, Hugh S. Johnson, Jesse Jones, Joseph P. Kennedy, Walter Lippmann, Huey Long, William G. McAdoo, G. Walter Mapp, Andrew Mellon, Eugene Meyer, Andrew J. Montague, R. Walton Moore, Henry Morgenthau, Robert L. Owen, George C. Peery, John G. Pollard, A. Willis Robertson, Eleanor Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Dave E. Satterfield, C. Bascom Slemp, Rixey Smith, Billy Sunday, Claude A. Swanson, Harry S. Truman, Joseph P. Tumulty, Oscar W. Underwood, Samuel Untermeyer, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Robert F. Wagner, Henry A. Wallace, Paul Moritz Warburg, Richard S. Whaley, William Allen White, John Skelton Williams, H. Parker Willis, Edith Bolling Wilson, Woodrow Wilson, Clifton A. Woodrum, and Walter Wyatt.
Contents List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  Personal correspondence of Carter Glass and Bernard Baruch extending over a period of years to about 1922; Newton D. Baker to Carter Glass regarding Wilson's "Confidential Documents" sent with letter, 20 January 1924, Baker to Carter Glass to obtain Glass' opinion of the use of the document in connection with the platform framed at the Democratic National convention of July 11, 1924; Carter Glass to Newton D. Baker asking him to examine Glass' book; Letters between Bernard Baruch and Carter Glass, 1920-22, 1936, regarding Baruch's book, Taking the Profits Out of War, and other matters; Folder of correspondence with Dr. [Edwin] Alderman; Carter Glass to Bernard Baruch, 29 March 1927, regarding the book, The Real Colonel House by Arthur Howden Smith; Carter Glass to Bernard Baruch regarding Arthur Howden Smith's article in the New York Herald Tribune, 2 April 1927; Bernard Baruch to Carter Glass regarding Carter Glass' book. An Adventure in Constructive Finance; Bernard Baruch to Carter Glass, 24 March 1926, in reference to Glass' piece on currency reform; Carter Glass to Baruch, 24 March 1926, regarding Colonel House; Carter Glass to Bernard Baruch, 18 October 1926, regarding Carter Glass' narrative on Federal Reserve legislation, written to destroy both Seymour and House; Bernard Baruch to Carter Glass suggesting that Glass write an article for "some magazine" refuting House; Folder of correspondence with John Stewart Bryan, 1932 regarding politics, speeches, personal friends, includes a few letters from Bernard Baruch; Folder of correspondence with Bernard Baruch; Folder of Bob Ainsworth letters, personal and political; Folder of Harry F. Byrd letters regarding state politics; Memorandum from correspondents of Harry F. Byrd and Carter Glass, said to be a statement of the Democratic platform of 1924, as Wilson desired it. "RS" initials on attached slip. Baker letters are also in this folder.
- Personal correspondence (C-D) (Box 2)
  A. Correspondence with Calvin Coolidge.
  B. Correspondence relating to state politics.
  C. Correspondence concerning the 1924 Democratic State Convention.
  D. Copy of the Virginia Democratic platform for 1924, which Carter Glass sent to several people, including George W. Norris at the Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia.
  E. Copies of newspaper articles dealing with Bishop James Cannon.
  F. Political and personal correspondence with Ed A. Christian: Answer to letter from Christian on October 1, 1928, Carter Glass stating that Robert L. Owen had nothing to do with the Federal Reserve Act other than to "permit it to be mangled in the Senate, which necessitated restoring.... its integrity in the conference committee of the two houses," despite the claims of Robert L. Owen to the contrary.
  G. Miscellaneous articles: Copy of a Virginia Democratic platform; Copies of several speeches by Carter Glass, including, "A Menacing 'Group Alliance'," and "Truth About the Federal Reserve System " (January, 1922); Congressional address made on December 15, 1924, by Edwin A. Alderman in memory of Woodrow Wilson; Editorial presenting the position of Carter Glass on agricultural loans by the Federal Reserve System; Article, January 18, 1922, in a Memphis newspaper, defending the Federal Reserve System against the critics claiming that system policies caused deflation following the war; Newspaper article, including figures, commenting briefly on a statement of the position of the Federal Reserve; Announcement of the opening of hearings under guidance of the Senate Banking and Currency Committee, aimed at changing banking laws to meet the severe depression condition of the 1930's.
  H. Correspondence with the Josephus Daniels, editor of a Raleigh, North Carolina, newspaper: Article describing the argument between Carter Glass and L. M. Williams, a Richmond, Virginia, banker, concerning Federal Reserve policy with respect to stock speculation; Editorial stating that, despite the opposition of bankers, Carter Glass should be entrusted with responsibility for perfecting legislation relating to banking; Answer to Josephus Daniels, Carter Glass expressing the opinion that real estate mortgages should not be made eligible for rediscount, since, "if that and kindred projects were followed, we would soon transform the Federal Reserve banks into investment banks, when they would no longer be liquid or able to respond to the demands of commerce"; Request made by Daniels for an opinion on a letter regarding real estate securities from the president of the American Mortgage Company occasioned Glass' remark.
  I. Envelope containing a series of memoranda concerning the Anti-Saloon League of America.
- Personal Correspondence (D-G) (Box 3)
  A. Personal References: Summary of the Carter Glass bill on banking of 1932 with special reference to changes which had been made or attempted; Memorandum showing Carter Glass' unfavorable attitude toward devaluation of the dollar; Copy of a statement by the Mississippi legislator refusing to vote on the question of remonetizing silver in the way that the State Senate had instructed.
  B. Honors and citations bestowed upon Carter Glass.
  C. Letter from H. D. Flood, State Democratic Committee.